A Guide to the William Whitsitt Papers, 1858-1909 (bulk 1896-1899)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
William Whitsitt Papers, 1858-1909 (bulk 1896-1899)
The Library of Virginia
24812
1.8 cu. ft. (6 boxes)
Whitsitt, William
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William H. Whitsitt, 16 July 1910
Alternative Form Available
Available on Misc. reels 37-39.
Biographical Information
William Heth Whitsitt (1841-1911) was born in Nashville, Tennessee. He was ordained a Baptist minister in 1862, and served in the Confederate Army. He was professor of Church history at the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary in Louisville, Ky., from 1872-1895, and as President from 1895-1899, when he was forced to resign. He served as professor of philosophy at Richmond College, now University of Richmond, Richmond, Va., from 1901-1910.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1858-1906, of William Whitsitt of Tennessee, consisting of correspondence, index cards, newspaper clippings, pamphlets, and notes. These papers are arranged chronologically in six boxes, and contain letters to William H. Whitsitt dealing almost entirely with the so-called Whitsitt controversy of 1896-1899 among Southern Baptists. In brief, Whitsitt asserted in an article in Johnson's Universal Cyclopedia that there had not been an unbroken continuance of the Baptist practice of immersion for adults seeking membership in the denomination. It was practically an article of faith among many Southern Baptists during that period that their ordinance of adult baptism by immersion had been handed down from generation to generation all the way back to New Testament times. Whitsitt's assertion appeared to many to be an undermining of Baptist legitimacy and authority.
The Whitsitt papers contain letters from theologians, educators, Baptist clergymen and laymen in all parts of the country. The letters range from open hostility and disbelief of Whitsitt's theory, to support and praise for his position. Especially interesting throughout the correspondence files are Whitsitt's annotations of the letters and notes he wrote regarding certain aspects of the controversy. Included among the correspondence are numerous newspaper clippings. Also included is correspondence from T.T. Eaton, editor of The Western Recorder, who led the opposition against Whitsitt. Whitsitt's 13 July 1898 resignation letter to the Seminary is included, along with correspondence with Richmond College in regards to a faculty position.
Other topics of the correspondence include publication of Whitsitt's books, correspondence with his wife, and the daily affairs of the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary such as, conventions, speeches, and pleas for donations. The Seminary received contributions from John D. Rockefeller and included in the collection are letters in regards to his donations. Also included is a report of the faculty of the Seminary for 1896-1897; pamphlet "After Whitsitt, What?: An open letter to the trustees of the Southern Baptist Theological Seminary" by S.C. Mitchell, 1899; Southern Baptist Theological Seminary treasurers report, 1899; pamphlet "Baptist World Congress, 1905"; and pamphlet "The Southern Baptist Theological Seminary Jubilee 1859-1909."
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1858-1895 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1896 January-February (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1896 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1896 June (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1896 July (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1896 August 1-20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1896 August 21-31 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1896 September 1-17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1896 September 18-25 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1896 September 26-30 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1896 October 1-15 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1896 October 16-31 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1896 November (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1896 December (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1897 January (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1897 February (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1897 March (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1897 April (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1897 May 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1897 May 18-31 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1897 June (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1897 July 1-12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1897 July 13-20 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1897 July 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1897 August 1-20 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1897 August 21-31 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1897 September 1-19 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1897 September 21-30 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1897 October 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1897 October 16-26 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1897 November (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1897 December (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1898 January (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1898 February (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1898 March 1-15 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1898 March 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1898 April (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1898 May (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1898 June (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1898 July 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1898 July 11-16 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1898 July 18-30 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1898 August (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1898 September (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1898 October (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1898 November (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1898 December (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1899 January (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1899 February (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1899 March (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1899 April (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1899 May 1-15 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1899 May 16-31 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 1899 June (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 1905-1906 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Correspondence, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- The Whitsitt Controversy, 1896-1899, written by William Whitsitt, ca. 1906 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Accession notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Index cards containing a chronological listing of correspondence, including date, correspondents name, and place, 1858-1898 February (Box 5)
- Index cards containing a chronological listing of correspondence, including correspondents name, place, and date, 1898 March-1909; and alphabetical index of correspondents and date of correspondence (some cards include birth and death dates of correspondents) (Box 6)